Guide to the R. A. (Robert A.) McConnell Papers, 1944-2000
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
R. A. (Robert A.) McConnell papers 1944-2000
McConnell, R. A. (Robert A.)
41.4 linear feet Extent: 19,514 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00866
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The R. A. (Robert A.) McConnell Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift, 1996-2008.
Biographical Note
Professor emeritus in Biology at University of Pittsburgh and specialist in parapsychology.
The collection is restricted until 2008. Users must obtain donor's permission. Contact a Reference Archivist.
Collection Overview
Collection (1996-0122) (11,500 items; 34.5 lin. ft.; 1944-1996) contains research materials in parapsychology spanning five decades; data and records from numerous parapsychology experiments (1947-1989); correspondence files, which include nearly all important scientists in the field (1944-1996); and various printed materials, among which are several boxes of psychic healing literature. Some papers document in great detail professional criticism, disputes, and controversies over several decades.
The addition (1997-0084) (3000 items; 6.0 lin. ft.; 1951-1991) includes research records (many having to do with funding for projects) and correspondence. Also includes copies of many of McConnell's publications (often two copies of each).
The addition (2000-0274) (3 items; 0.2 lin. ft.; 2000) to the collection contains a copy of McConnell's book Joyride to Infinity (2000), related items, and printouts of McConnell's website: www.ramcconnell.com. (No container list was created for this addition.)
The addition (2000-0431) (8 items; 0.1 lin. ft.; 2000) contains statements and articles by McConnell summing up his beliefs and positions on the existence of experimental phenomenon, the importance of parapsychology, and arguments against scientists who claim that parapsychological phenomena do not exist. (No container list was created for this addition.)
The addition (2008-0290) (4500 items; 6 lin. ft.; 1953-1990s) consists largely of individual correspondence (organized alphabetically), committee materials, and committee correspondence.
Subject Headings
Parapsychologists -- United States -- Correspondence; Parapsychology and science; Extrasensory perception; Federation of American Scientists; Parapsychology -- Research; Mental healing; Psychokinesis; Psychometry (Parapsychology); Scientists-attitudes
Contents of Collection
- Accession (1996-0122)
  Note: See donor's original inventory in CCF for fuller details and explanations of abbreviations. The original box numbers are indicated in the container list below.
  - (Box 1)
    Old box numbers 001-002
    - Experiment PKPL-2 (Box 1)
  - (Box 2)
    Old box numbers 002-004
    - Experiment PKPL-2 (Box 2)
  - (Box 3)
    Old box numbers 004-005
    - Experiment PKPL-2 (Box 3)
    - Experiment DCM et al. (Box 3)
  - (Box 4)
    Old box numbers 006-007
    - Experiment DCM et al. (Box 4)
  - (Box 5)
    Old box numbers 007-008
    - Experiment DCM et al. (Box 5)
  - (Box 6)
    Old box numbers 008-010
    - Experiment DCM et al. (Box 6)
    - Correspondence: J. Eisenbud (Box 6)
    - 1 copy, The world of Ted Serios (Box 6)
  - (Box 7)
    Old box numbers 010-011
    - Correspondence: J. Eisenbud (Box 7)
    - 1 copy, The world of Ted Serios (Box 7)
  - (Box 8)
    Old box numbers 011-012
    - Correspondence: G. R. Schmeidler (Box 8)
    - Correspondence and Experiments -- Haakon Forwald (Box 8)
  - (Box 9)
    Old box numbers 013-014
    - Correspondence: People Series 1, A-H (Box 9)
  - (Box 10)
    Old box numbers 015-016
    - Correspondence: People Series 1, J-R (Box 10)
  - (Box 11)
    Old box numbers 017-018
    - Correspondence: People Series 1, S-Z (Box 11)
    - Correspondence: Critics of Parapsychology and Their Victims (Box 11)
  - (Box 12)
    Old box numbers 018-019
    - Critics of Parapsychology (Box 12)
    - Giving of Books and Papers, 1982-1987, EEP-0 to EEP-3 (Box 12)
  - (Box 13)
    Old box numbers 020-021
    - 1975-1978,Seven Educational Activities (Box 13)
    - Correspondence: Selected Persons (Box 13)
  - (Box 14)
    Old box numbers 022-024
    - Correspondence: Selected Persons and Organizations (Box 14)
  - (Box 15)
    Old box numbers 024-026
    - Correspondence: Selected Persons and Organizations (Box 15)
    - Psychic Healing Literature, Miscellaneous (Box 15)
  - (Box 16)
    Old box numbers 026-028
    - Psychic Healing Literature, Miscellaneous (Box 16)
    - Psychic Healing Literature, Selected (Box 16)
  - (Box 17)
    Old box numbers 028-030
    - Psychic Healing Literature, Selected (Box 17)
    - Parapsychological Association Records, 1957-1961 (Box 17)
    - Parapsychological Association Records, 1962-1965 (Box 17)
  - (Box 18)
    Old box numbers 030-032
    Needs more processing before use.
    - Parapsychological Association Records, 1966-1972(030) (Box 18)
      includes PA joins the AAAS, 1969-1980
    - Parapsychological Association Records, 1973-1986(031) (Box 18)
    - Parapsychological Association Records, 1987and earlier records (032) (Box 18)
  - (Box 19)
    Old box numbers 032-034
    - Parapsychological Association Records, 1987-1994 (Box 19)
    - USSR Relations (Box 19)
  - (Box 20)
    Old box numbers 034-035
    - USSR Relations (Box 20)
    - Giving of Books and Papers, 1987-1988,EEP-4 to EEP-11 (Box 20)
  - (Box 21)
    Old box numbers 036-037
    - Mailings of 1989 Marchto 1989 August,EEP-12 to EEP-13 (Box 21)
    - National Academy of Sciences Mailings, 1989,EEP-14 to EEP-15 (Box 21)
  - (Box 22)
    Old box numbers 037-039
    - National Academy of Sciences Mailings, end of EEP-15 (Box 22)
    - Fraud and Self-Deception (Box 22)
    - EEP-16 Mailings, 1990 Octoberto 1991 June (Box 22)
  - (Box 23)
    Old box numbers 039-040
    - EEP-16 Mailings (cont.) - end (Box 23)
    - Six Educational Activities, 1968-1974 (Box 23)
- Accession (1997-0084), 5 Boxes (Box 23)
  The addition (1997-0084) (3500 items; 6.5 lin. ft.; 1951-1997) contains research records (many having to do with funding for projects) and correspondence. Also includes copies of many of McConnell's publications (often two copies of each). This addition also includes correspondence and McConnell's letters with the FLAS (Federation of American Scientists). Correspondence is arranged according to surname and date; FLFAS corresondence was organized by R.A. McConnell and assigned numerical values (key for values is provided in Box 5).
  - Financial Documents, 1964-1992 (Box 1)
    - Carlson detailed expense reports, 1967-1974, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - A. W. Mellon detailed expense reports, 1967-1979, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - A. W. monthly summaries, 1974-1992, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - A. W. payroll expenses, 1964-1986, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Mellon Trust Report Excerpts, 1930s-1980s (Box 1)
    - Payments to M.L. Anderson, 1959-1962 (Box 1)
    - McConnell Research Accounts, 1959-1960s (Box 1)
    - Shanti Foundation (Mrs. Carlson), 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Rockefeller Brothers (Box 2)
    - McConnell Fund for Miscellaneous Gifts, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - McConnell Fund Summaries, 1986-1996 (Box 2)
    - William McDougall Grant (Box 2)
    - New World Foundation (Box 2)
    - W. G. and J. V. Stone Foundation (Box 2)
  - Publications and Correspondence, 1951-1997 (Box 2)
    - Publications, 1961-1996, 72 folders (Box 2)
    - Print Material, 1958-1996, 11 prints (Box 3)
    - "Parapsychology in Retrospect," 1987 facsimile (Box 3)
    - Wyckoff, George W., 1982-1983 (Box 3)
    - Lockhart, George D., 1968-1994 (Box 3)
    - Walker, John, 1982-1991 (Box 3)
    - A. W. Mellon Trust, 1951-Dec. 1978, 14 folders (Box 3)
    - A. W. Mellon Trust, 1978-1991, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Parapsychology Research, 1964-1979, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Halliday, D., 1952 (Box 4)
    - Schmidt, A. W., 1968-1980, 6 folders (Box 4)
    - Research Administration, 1958-1953, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1951 (Box 4)
    - University of Pittsburgh, 1944-1953 (Box 4)
    - Self-Evaluation Reports, 1976-1981 (Box 4)
    - Biological Sciences at Pittsburg, 1969-1988 (Box 4)
    - Pollard, Ernest, 1945 (Box 4)
    - House Meetings, 1951-1954 (Box 4)
    - Statistical Memo, 1952 (Box 4)
    - Parapsychology of Pittsburg, 1989 (Box 4)
    - Goldstein, Bruce, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Antleman, Seymour, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Gerjuoy, Edward 1978 (Box 4)
    - Crawford, S. C., 1951 (Box 4)
    - Longenecter, H. E., 1951 (Box 4)
    - Rosenburg, Jerome L., 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Posvar, W. W., 2 folders (Box 4)
    - O'Connor, John Dennis, 1991-1995, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Rockefeller Brothers correspondence, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - "The Scientific Autobiography of a Parapsychologist," 1998 (Box 4)
    - FLFAS (Federation of American Scientists) letters, 1975-1976, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - FLFAS Foreign Mailing, 1976 (Box 5)
    - FLFAS correspondence key (Box 5)
    - FLFAS correspondence A-F, 1970s (Box 5)
    - FLFAS correspondence G-M, 1970s (Box 5)
    - FLFAS correspondence N-S, 1970s (Box 5)
    - FLFAS correspondence T-Z, 1970s (Box 5)
    - FLFAS unprocessed correspondence, 1976-1997 (Box 5)
    - "Scientific Freedom and Responsiblity," 1975 (Box 5)
- Accession (2000-0274) and Accession (2000-0431), 1 Box (Box 5)
  The addition (2000-0274) (3 items; 0.2 lin. ft.; 2000) contains a copy of McConnell's book Joyride to Infinity (2000), related items, and printouts of McConnell's website: www.ramcconnell.com.
  The addition (2000-0431) (8 items; 0.1 lin. ft.; 2000) includes statements and articles by McConnell summarizing his beliefs and positions on the existence of experimental phenomenon, the importance of parapsychology, and arguments against scientists who claim that parapsychological phenomena do not exist. This material can also be found on McConnell's website.
- Accession (2008-0290), 1953-1990s, 10 Boxes (Box 5)
  The addition (2008-0290) (4500 items; 6 lin. ft.; 1953-1990s) consists largely of individual correspondence (organized alphabetically), committee materials, and committee correspondence. For a more complete description of the materials, please see the donor's inventory in the Collection Control File.
  This accession is restricted. Please contact Reference Services with questions.
  - RAM's Committee and its members correspondence, 1953-1985 (Box 1)
  - RAM's Committee and its members correspondence, 1953-1985 (Box 2)
  - Individual Correspondence, A-B (Box 2)
    - Alexander, Dr. John B. (Box 2)
    - Alvarado, Carlos S. (Box 2)
    - Atkinson, Prof. Richard C. (Box 2)
    - Bauer, Eberhard (Box 2)
    - Beardsley, Dr. Wallace (Box 2)
    - Bell, Prof. Daniel (Box 2)
    - Benveniste, Jacques (Box 2)
    - Beloff, Dr. John (Box 2)
    - Berger, Arthur (Box 2)
    - Berger, Dr. Rick (Box 2)
    - Bird, Christopher (Box 2)
    - Blackmore, Susan (Box 2)
    - Blakemore, Dr. Colin (Box 2)
    - Bowles, Norma (Box 2)
    - Braud, Dr. William G., (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Individual Correspondence, B-E (Box 3)
    - Braude, Dr. Stephen (Box 3)
    - Bro, Harmon (Box 3)
    - Broughton, Dr. Richard (Box 3)
    - Brown, Dr. Frederick (Box 3)
    - Brown, Mr. Burke (Box 3)
    - Brier, Bob (Box 3)
    - Burdick, Dr. Donald S (Box 3)
    - Cardena, C. E. (Box 3)
    - Carson, Prof. Walter (Box 3)
    - Cassoli, Dr. Piero, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Chance, Dr. Britton (Box 3)
    - Chauvin, Dr. Remy (Box 3)
    - Child, Dr. Irvin, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Chomsky, Dr. Noam (Box 3)
    - Chopra, Deepak (Box 3)
    - Clark, Lord Kenneth (Box 3)
    - Cohen, Dr. Sidney (Box 3)
    - Collins, H. M. (Box 3)
    - Cook, Emily, (5 folders) (Box 3)
    - Cooper, Topher (Box 3)
    - Crandall, James (Box 3)
    - Cuthbert, Chester (Box 3)
    - Cutten, John (Box 3)
    - Darwin, Sir Charles (Box 3)
    - David, Mrs. Farilla (Box 3)
    - Davis, R. Kingsley (Box 3)
    - Davis, Prof. W. Jackson (Box 3)
    - Davison, Mr. Jack (Box 3)
    - Dawes, Prof. Robyn (Box 3)
    - Dean, Mr. Douglas (Box 3)
    - Don, Dr. Norman, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Dossey, Larry (Box 3)
    - Drewes, Athena (Box 3)
    - Drucker, Dr. Sally Ann (Box 3)
    - Dunne, Brenda J. (Box 3)
    - Duplessis, Dr. Yvonne (Box 3)
    - Ebon, Martin (Box 3)
    - Eccles, Sir John C. (Box 3)
    - Edison, Theodore M. (Box 3)
    - Edwards, Tony (Box 3)
    - Eisenberg, Anne (Box 3)
    - Eisenberg, Dr. Howard (Box 3)
  - Individual Correspondence, E-H (Box 4)
    - Elchert, Ms. Casey (Box 4)
    - Ejvegaard, Dr. Rolf (Box 4)
    - Evans, Hilary (Box 4)
    - Eysenck, Dr. H. J. (Box 4)
    - Felsenfeld, Dr. Gary (Box 4)
    - Feola, Jose M. (Box 4)
    - Firebrace, Brig. R. C. (Box 4)
    - Flick, Barbara (Box 4)
    - Frank, Dr. Jerome (Box 4)
    - Franklin, Dr. Wilbur, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - (Box 4)
    - Gell-Mann, Dr. Murray (Box 4)
    - Geller, Uri (Box 4)
    - Gofman, John W. (Box 4)
    - Grad, Dr. Bernard (Box 4)
    - Granero, Mirta (Box 4)
    - Greenwood, Joseph A. (Box 4)
    - Greyson, Dr. Bruce (Box 4)
    - Haisch, Dr. Barnhard (Box 4)
    - Harary, Keith (Box 4)
    - Haraldsson, Dr. Erlandur (Box 4)
    - Harman, Willis (Box 4)
    - Hastings, Dr. Arthur J. (Box 4)
    - Hovelmann, Gerd H. (Box 4)
    - Humphreys, Lloyd G., (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Individual Correspondence, H-K (Box 5)
    - Hyman, Ray, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Inglis, David (Box 5)
    - Jahn, Dr. Robert, (5 folders) (Box 5)
    - Johnson, Dr. Martin (Box 5)
    - Josephson, D. B. D. (Box 5)
    - Kahn, Richard D. (Box 5)
    - Kahn, Mr. S. David (Box 5)
    - Keil, Prof. H. H. Jurgen, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Kelly, Dr. Edward F., (8 folders) (Box 5)
    - Krippner, Dr. Stanley, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Kuhn, Thomas S., (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Individual Correspondence, L-M (Box 6)
    - Laibow, Dr. Rima, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Lamm, Gov. Richard, (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - Lattimore, Owen (Box 6)
    - LeShan, Lawrence, (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - Libby, Dr. William (Box 6)
    - Lucadou, Dr. Walter (Box 6)
    - Luke, Wanda (Box 6)
    - Maher, Dr. Michaeleen (Box 6)
    - Maricic, Dr. S. (Box 6)
    - Marks, Prof. David (Box 6)
    - Matlock, Mr. James (Box 6)
    - Mauskopf, Dr. Seymour (Box 6)
    - May,Dr. Edwin, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - McBeath, Dr. Michael (Box 6)
    - McCarthy, Dr. Donald (Box 6)
    - McClenon, James (Box 6)
    - McMahan, Elizabeth (Box 6)
    - Meehl, P. E., (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Millar, Dr. Brian (Box 6)
    - Milton, Dr. Julie (Box 6)
    - Mishlove, Dr. Jeffrey, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Mitchell, Dr. Edgar, (4 of 5 folders) (Box 6)
  - Individual Correspondence, M-Q (Box 7)
    - Mitchell, Dr. Edgar, (5 of 5 folders) (Box 7)
    - Montis, Dr. Hernandez (Box 7)
    - Morris, Dr. Robert L., (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - Morrison, Dr. Philip (Box 7)
    - Moyers, Bill (Box 7)
    - Murphy, Gardner & Lois (Box 7)
    - Nelson, Dr. Roger (Box 7)
    - Palmer, Dr. John (Box 7)
    - Pell, Sen. Claiborne (Box 7)
    - Phillips, Dr. Peter (Box 7)
    - Pierce, Mr. Henry, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Pilkington, RoseMarie (Box 7)
    - Pomeranz, Dr. Bruce (Box 7)
    - Powell, Kenneth, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Prince of Wales (Prince Charles) (Box 7)
    - Puthoff, Dr. Hal, (5 folders) (Box 7)
    - Quinn, Dr. Janet F. (Box 7)
  - Individual Correspondence, R-S (Box 8)
    - Radin, Dr. Dean, (5 folders) (Box 8)
    - Reed, C. B. (Box 8)
    - Richards, Douglas G. (Box 8)
    - Riesman, Prof. David (Box 8)
    - Roberts, Dr. Richard B. (Box 8)
    - Robinson, Diana (Box 8)
    - Rockwell, Ted, (9 folders) (Box 8)
    - Roll, William G. (Box 8)
    - Roney-Dougal, Serena (Box 8)
    - Rosen, Prof. Steven (Box 8)
    - Rosenberg, A. I., Esq. (Box 8)
    - Rubik, Beverly (Box 8)
    - Rush, Joseph (Box 8)
    - Sagan, Dr. Carl (Box 8)
    - Sargent, Barbara (Box 8)
    - Schechter, Dr. Ephraim, (1 of 2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Individual Correspondence, S (Box 9)
    - Schechter, Dr. Ephraim, (2 of 2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Schlitz, Dr. Marilyn, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Schmeidler, Dr. Gertrude, (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - Schmidt, Dr. Helmit, (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - Schwartz, Stephan A. (Box 9)
    - Schwarz, Dr. Berthold E., (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Scriven, Dr. M. (Box 9)
    - Snowden, Mrs Ruth J. (Box 9)
    - Solfvin, Dr. Jerry (Box 9)
    - Stanford, Dr. Rex, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Stevension, Dr. Ian, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Stokes, Douglas M. (Box 9)
    - Strong, Richard, (1 of 2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Individual Correspondence, S-Z (Box 10)
    - Strong, Richard, (2 of 2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Swann, Ingo (Box 10)
    - Tart, Dr. Charles (Box 10)
    - Taylor, Dr. Eugene (Box 10)
    - Taylor, John G. (Box 10)
    - Thalbourne, Michael A., (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Truzzi, Dr. Marcello (Box 10)
    - Van de Castle, Dr. Robert (Box 10)
    - Van Over, Mr. Raymond (Box 10)
    - Vassy, Zoltan (Box 10)
    - Vilenskaya, Larissa (Box 10)
    - Weiner, Debra (Box 10)
    - West, Dr. Donald (Box 10)
    - Westrum, Ron (Box 10)
    - Wheatley, Dr. James (Box 10)
    - Walker, Dr. Evan Harris (Box 10)
    - Wilson, Dr. Richard (Box 10)
    - Wirth, Daniel (Box 10)
    - Wolfe, C. Holmes (Box 10)
    - Wolman, Dr. Benjamin (Box 10)
    - Wunder, Dr. Charles (Box 10)
    - Zigmond, Dr. Michael (Box 10)